Robert Di Domenica Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Robert Di Domenica Collection 1900-1998 (bulk 1957-1993)
ML31.D55
Di Domenica, Robert, 1927-
2200 items 43 containers 15 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
American composer, flutist and music educator. Music manuscripts and printed music by the composer, performance programs, materials relating to his teaching career, a small amount of correspondence, biographical material, writings, photographs and six paintings by the composer.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Bender, Ellen, 1947-; Di Domenica, Leona.; Di Domenica, Leona.; Di Domenica, Robert, 1927-; Di Domenica, Robert, 1927-; Di Domenica, Robert, 1927- --Correspondence.
Form/Genre
Correspondence.; Paintings (Visual works); Photographic prints.; Programs (Documents)
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Mr. Di Domenica, 1994 and 1998.
Transfers
Sound recordings and video tapes have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division.
Related Material
Twenty-eight audio tapes, three compact discs and three video tapes mostly contain performances of Di Domenica's music. Two of the five video tapes contain interviews with him. Di Domenica was involved in the production of the compact discs. All of this material is located in the Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division, Library of Congress.
Access and Restrictions
The Robert Di Domenica Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Performing Arts Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use. Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Robert Di Domenica was born in New York City on March 4, 1927. His father, Angelo, was active in his church choir. Robert received a degree in music education from New York University in 1951 and continued private study in composition with Wallingford Riegger and Josef Schmid. He studied the flute under Harold Bennett.
As a flutist he has performed with the New York City Opera, the New York Philharmonic, the Modern Jazz Quartet and the Bach Aria Group, among others. As a teacher he has taught the flute privately and has served on the faculties of the Greenwich House Music School and the Henry Street Settlement. In 1969 he joined the faculty of the New England Conservatory of Music and eventually became dean.
Mr. Di Domenica has been composing since he served in the Navy in World War II. His first serious work, Sonata for Flute and Piano, was written in 1957. He has produced a wide variety of works. His opera The Balcony premiered at the Bolshoi, with Sarah Caldwell conducting. Now retired, Mr. Di Domenica is still composing.
Among his awards are a Guggenheim Fellowship in 1972, and commissions from the Goethe Institute of Boston and the Plymouth Symphony.
In 1951 he married Leona Knopf, a gifted pianist. She has been the interpreter of her husband’s piano works. She has also collaborated with him in his work, including the piano-vocal scores of The Balcony and The Scarlet Letter. David, Peter Josef (who married Patsy Treglis), and Claude Robert (who married Bessie Hadley) are their three sons. They also have four grandchildren. Leona Knopf died on May 11, 1998. Robert Di Domenica married Ellen Bender, a composer, flutist and teacher, on April 16, 1999.
Scope and Content Note
Robert Di Domenica has had a notable career as a flutist, composer, and music educator. The collection reflects all three of these activities. However, the majority of the material relates to his endeavors as a composer. The collection includes the manuscripts of compositions from his student days through his mature works. Mr. Di Domenica is still composing, and the library hopes to receive future manuscripts.
There is a relatively complete collection of programs reflecting Di Domenica’s activities both as a composer and a performer. The collection also includes material relating to his career as an educator, including lesson plans, papers by his students and evaluations.
There is a small amount of correspondence, biographical material on Mr. Di Domenica and his relatives, writings by Di Domenica, and photographs. There are six paintings done by Mr. Di Domenica.
Organization of the Robert Di Domenica Collection
The Robert Di Domenica Collection is organized into 10 series:
Music
Biographical Material
Correspondence
Writings
Recording and Publications Material
Teaching Materials
Iconography
Clippings
Programs
Other Material
http://lccn.loc.gov/2006568219
Container List
- Music (Box 1-37)
  The first 36 boxes contain Robert Di Domenica’s musical compositions, arranged alphabetically by title. There is material relating to Ellen Bender’s opera, Rappaccini’s Daughter for which Di Domenica wrote the libretto. There is also a small amount of printed music, which evidently belonged to Leona Knopf Di Domenica.
  - Music by R. Di Domenica (Box 1-36)
    - Arrangements for chamber ensemble, soprano and tape: final manuscript, [(1979) final original manuscript (transparency) 58 pages plus title page and instrumentation page] (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Arrangements for soprano, flute (piccolo and alto flute), clarinet (bass clarinet), violin, cello, percussion, and tape: original manuscript (book 1) with laid in material, [(1979) original manuscript (3 books) also rows, program notes, course material, analysis] (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Arrangements for soprano, flute, clarinet, violin, cello, percussion, and tape: original manuscript (book 2), [see 1/2] (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Arrangements for soprano, flute, clarinet, violin, cello, percussion, and tape: original manuscript (book 3), [see 1/2] (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Art of the row for solo piano: final original ms., [(1989) final original manuscript (transparency) 61 pages plus title page and "description" page] (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Art of the row for solo piano: original ms., also class examples, [(1989) original manuscript (1 loose leaf notebook) also: class examples, in front of notebook] (Box-folder 1/6)
    - "Bach" counterpoint (book 1) (Box-folder 2/1)
    - "Bach" counterpoint (book 2) with laid in material (Box-folder 2/2)
    - "Bach" counterpoint (book 3) (Box-folder 2/3)
    - "Bach" counterpoint (book 4) (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Balcony- orchestral score: front matter and Act I, scene 1-3, [(1972) an opera in two acts based of Jean Genet's The Balcony. Libretto by Robert Di Domenica. Orchestral score: 416 pages plus title page, "character" page, "orchestra" page] (Box-folder 3/1)
    - Balcony- orchestral score: Act I, scene 4-5, [see 3/1] (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Balcony- orchestral score: Act II, [see 3/1] (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Balcony- vocal score, final original manuscript: front matter and Act I, [(1972) an opera in two acts based on Jean Genet's The Balcony. Libretto by Robert Di Domenica. Vocal score by Leona Di Domenica. 247 pages plus "character" page] (Box-folder 4/1)
    - Balcony- vocal score, final original manuscript: Act II, [see 4/1] (Box-folder 4/2)
    - Balcony, rows, [(1972) (an opera in two acts) all rows The Balcony] (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Balcony, notebook: Act I, scene 1 (Box-folder 4/4)
    - Balcony, notebook: Act I, scene 2 (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Balcony, notebook: Act I, scene 2 (cont.) (Box-folder 5/2)
    - Balcony, notebook: Act I, scene 3 (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Balcony, notebook: Act I, scenes 4-5 (Box-folder 5/4)
    - Balcony, notebook: Act I, scene 5 (cont.) (Box-folder 5/5)
    - Balcony, notebook: Act II, scene 1 (Box-folder 6/1)
    - Balcony, notebook: Act II, scenes 2-3 (Box-folder 6/2)
    - Balcony, notebook: Act II, scene 4 (Box-folder 6/3)
    - Balcony, notebook: Act II, scene 4 (cont.) (Box-folder 6/4)
    - Balcony, notebook with laid in material: Act II, scene 4 (cont.) and exit music (Box-folder 6/5)
    - Balcony, libretto, [My first opera, based on Jean Genet's play The Balcony. The libretto is by myself, published during the writing of the opera] (Box-folder 6/6)
    - Beatrice Cenci, original orchestral score: front matter and Act I, [(1993) original transparency orchestral score, 851 pages plus title page and pages “a” and “b.” An opera in three acts based on Alberto Moravia's play Beatrice Cenci. This is the second opera in a trilogy: Francesco Cenci, Beatrice Cenci, The Cenci. Libretto by the composer.] (Box-folder 7/1)
    - Beatrice Cenci, original orchestral score: Act I (cont.), [see 7/1] (Box-folder 7/2)
    - Beatrice Cenci, original orchestral score: Act II, [see 7/1] (Box-folder 7/3)
    - Beatrice Cenci, original orchestral score: Act II (cont.), [see 7/1] (Box-folder 8/1)
    - Beatrice Cenci, original orchestral score: Act III, [see 7/1] (Box-folder 8/2)
    - Beatrice Cenci, original orchestral score: Act III (cont.), [see 7/1] (Box-folder 8/3)
    - Beatrice Cenci, piano/vocal score: front matter and Act I, scenes 1-5, [Original pencil manuscript of piano-vocal score of Beatrice Cenci. An opera in 3 acts, 638 pages] (Box-folder 9/1)
    - Beatrice Cenci, piano/vocal score: Act I, scenes 6-10, [see 9/1] (Box-folder 9/2)
    - Beatrice Cenci, piano/vocal score: Act II, scenes 1-4, [see 9/1] (Box-folder 9/3)
    - Beatrice Cenci, piano/vocal score: Act II, scenes 5-10, [see 9/1] (Box-folder 10/1)
    - Beatrice Cenci, piano/vocal score: Act III, scene 1, [see 9/1] (Box-folder 10/2)
    - Beatrice Cenci, piano/vocal score: Act III, scenes 2-5, [see 9/1] (Box-folder 10/3)
    - Beatrice Cenci, piano/vocal score: epilogue, [see 9/1] (Box-folder 10/4)
    - Black poems for baritone voice, piano, tape: final original ms., [(1976) final original manuscript (transparencies) 37 pages including title page (no transparencies for pre-taped parts located yet)] (Box-folder 11/1)
    - Black poems for baritone voice, piano, tape: original ms. and rows, [(1976) original manuscript (1 notebook) (and 11 different rows used)] (Box-folder 11/2)
    - Cenci, front matter and orchestral score, [original transparency orchestral score. A drama with music, based on Shelley's (Act Five) The Cenci. 107 pages plus title page and pages “a” and “b.” Libretto by R. Di Domenica.] (Box-folder 12/1)
    - Cenci, orchestral score: notebook 1 with laid in material, [Original pencil manuscript (orchestral score) (in 3 notebooks and inserted loose pages) (row used in opera in book 1). None of the abundant dialogue is in this manuscript. Refer to original manuscript (final form- transparencies)] (Box-folder 12/2)
    - Cenci, orchestral score: notebook 2, [see 12/2] (Box-folder 12/3)
    - Cenci, orchestral score: notebook 3 with laid in material, [see 12/2] (Box-folder 12/4)
    - Cenci, piano/vocal score (photocopy), [Piano-vocal score (piano part only) 39 pages in one notebook and loose pages 40-45. Attached to the notebook is a spiral bound photocopy which is the final complete form (vocal parts, dialogue). It is 69 pages plus a title page, a character page (a) and orchestra-scenario page (b)] (Box-folder 12/5)
    - Cenci, piano/vocal score: piano part, [see 12/5] (Box-folder 12/6)
    - Composition in the forms, notebook 1 (Box-folder 13/1)
    - Composition in the forms, notebook 2 with laid in material (Box-folder 13/2)
    - Composition in the forms, notebook 3 with laid in material (Box-folder 13/3)
    - Composition in the forms, notebook 4 with laid in material (Box-folder 13/4)
    - Composition in the forms, notebook 5 with laid in material (Box-folder 13/5)
    - Concerto for violin and chamber orchestra, final score, [(1962) final manuscripts (transparencies) Score in my manuscript: 112 pages including title/instrumentation page] (Box-folder 14/1)
    - Concerto for violin and chamber orchestra, original ms. and laid in material, [(1962) original manuscript (also rows)] (Box-folder 14/2)
    - Concerto for violin and chamber orchestra, parts (11), [solo violin 12pp., flute 8pp., oboe 8pp., clarinet 8pp., horn 9pp., bassoon 9pp., violin-1 9pp., violin-2 9pp., viola 10pp, bass 9pp.] (Box-folder 14/3)
    - Concerto for wind quintet, strings, and timpani; final original ms., [(1964) final original manuscript (ink on transparencies) score: 115 pages] (Box-folder 15/1)
    - Concerto for wind quintet, strings, and timpani; final original parts- photocopies (11), [(1964) photocopy (of my original manuscript) bound parts: 1 of each string part, but the work should be performed with a string section] (Box-folder 15/2)
    - Concerto for wind quintet, strings, and timpani, original ms.: movement I and additional material, [(1964) original manuscript (loose pages and two books) (also rows)] (Box-folder 15/3)
    - Concerto for wind quintet, strings, and timpani, original ms.: movement II, [see 15/3] (Box-folder 15/4)
    - Concerto for wind quintet, strings, and timpani, original ms.: movements II (cont.) and III, [see 15/3] (Box-folder 15/5)
    - Concord revisited for solo piano and wind ensemble (with soprano and baritone voice and tape), final original ms., [(1978) final original manuscript (transparency) 75 pages plus title page and instrumental page] (Box-folder 15/6)
    - Dream journeys, final original ms., [(1984) written in 1985 but closer to ‘84 in reality. Final original manuscript (transparency) 33 pages plus title page and instrumentation page] (Box-folder 16/1)
    - Dream journeys, original ms.: notebook 1 and laid in material, [(1984) original manuscript (in 2 notebooks and loose pages) not in a clear order] (Box-folder 16/2)
    - Dream journeys, original ms.: notebook 2 and laid in material, [see 16/2] (Box-folder 16/3)
    - Dream journeys, published score (2 copies), [Also: actual publication- Margun Music., Inc.] (Box-folder 16/4)
    - Eleven short pieces, final original ms., [(1973) final original manuscript (transparency) 16 pages including title page (which is page 1)] (Box-folder 16/5)
    - Eleven short pieces, original ms., [original manuscript (and 11 different rows used in piece)] (Box-folder 16/6)
    - First kiss of love, final ms., [(1960) final original manuscript (ink on transparency) 5 pages] (Box-folder 16/7)
    - First kiss of love, original ms. and laid in material, [original manuscript (incomplete row chart and typed text)] (Box-folder 16/8)
    - First kiss of love, published copies (2 copies), [actual publication- Edition Musicus] (Box-folder 16/9)
    - Four movements for piano, final ms., [(1959) final original manuscript (transparency) 10 pages plus printed title page] (Box-folder 16/10)
    - Four movements for piano, original ms., [(1959) original manuscript (no row charts)] (Box-folder 16/11)
    - Four short songs, final original ms., [(1975) flute, clarinet in B♭, violin, cello and piano. Final original manuscript (transparencies)] (Box-folder 17/1)
    - Four short songs, original ms., (1975) flute, clarinet in B♭, violin, cello and piano. Original manuscript (1 notebook) plus printed texts (and row chart)] (Box-folder 17/2)
    - Four short songs, final original ms.- parts (5), [all parts except piano (which plays from 17/1)] (Box-folder 17/3)
    - Francesco Cenci, final original score: front material and Act I, [(1996) original manuscript (transparency) an opera in two acts. First part of a trilogy (Francesco Cenci, Beatrice Cenci, The Cenci) 297 pages plus title page and pp. a, b, c] (Box-folder 17/4)
    - Francesco Cenci, final original orchestral score: Act II, [see 17/4] (Box-folder 17/5)
    - Francesco Cenci, original orchestral ms.: notebook 1, [(an opera in two acts) original pencil manuscript (orchestral score) (in 6 notebooks and inserted in loose pages) (Rows used in opera in book 1)] (Box-folder 18/1)
    - Francesco Cenci, original orchestral ms.: notebook 2, [see 18/1] (Box-folder 18/2)
    - Francesco Cenci, original orchestral ms.: notebook 3, [see 18/1] (Box-folder 18/3)
    - Francesco Cenci, original orchestral ms.: notebook 4, [see 18/1] (Box-folder 18/4)
    - Francesco Cenci, original orchestral ms.: notebook 5 with laid in material, [see 18/1] (Box-folder 18/5)
    - Francesco Cenci, original orchestral ms.: notebook 6 with laid in material, [see 18/1] (Box-folder 18/6)
    - Francesco Cenci, piano/vocal score: notebook 1, [an opera in two acts, piano-vocal score, original pencil manuscript (used to make pencil master) (in 3 notebooks- no title page, instrumentation etc.)] (Box-folder 19/1)
    - Francesco Cenci, piano/vocal score: notebook 2, [see 19/2] (Box-folder 19/2)
    - Francesco Cenci, piano/vocal score: notebook 3, [see 19/2] (Box-folder 19/3)
    - Gone are the rivers and the eagles, final original ms., [(1992) variations for orchestra on two songs of Charles Ives, 49 pages plus title page and instrumentation (and description) page, final original manuscript (transparency)] (Box-folder 19/4)
    - Gone are the rivers and the eagles, original ms. and analysis, [original manuscript (1 notebook and loose pages) (rows) also: 7 pages of analysis] (Box-folder 19/5)
    - Harmony, notebook 1 and laid in material (Box-folder 19/6)
    - Harmony, notebook 2 (Box-folder 20/1)
    - Harmony, notebook 3 (Box-folder 20/2)
    - Harmony, notebook 4 and laid in material (Box-folder 20/3)
    - Harmony, notebook 5 (Box-folder 20/4)
    - Harmony, notebook 6 (Box-folder 20/5)
    - Harmony, notebook 8 (Box-folder 20/6)
    - Hebrew melodies, final ms., [(1983) for soprano, violin and piano, final original manuscript(transparencies) 28 pages plus title page and page of printed text] (Box-folder 21/1)
    - Hebrew melodies, original ms. with laid in material and other material, [(1983) for soprano, violin and piano, original manuscript (1 notebook) (and row chart) also printed texts] (Box-folder 21/2)
    - Hebrew melodies, violin part, [5 pages] (Box-folder 21/3)
    - Holy colophon, final ms., [(1980) for orchestra, chorus, soprano and tenor. Final original manuscript (transparency) 75 pages plus title page, plus intermediate page, plus 4 pages of text] (Box-folder 21/4)
    - Holy colophon, original ms.- notebook, [(1980) for orchestra, chorus, soprano and tenor (original manuscripts, rows, programs, some of text)] (Box-folder 21/5)
    - Holy colophon, original ms.- misc. material, [see 21/5] (Box-folder 21/6)
    - Holy colophon, vocal parts (tenor and soprano in ms., chorus in photocopy), [(1980) for orchestra, chorus, soprano and tenor. Original manuscript (transparencies) of vocal parts. Soprano parts: 8 pages plus title page. Tenor part: 8 pages plus title page. Tenor part: 8 pages plus title page. Chorus part (photocopy): 10 pages] (Box-folder 21/7)
    - Improvisations, final ms., [(1974) final original manuscript (transparency) 16 pages] (Box-folder 21/8)
    - Improvisations, original ms., [(1974) final original manuscript (and row chart)] (Box-folder 21/9)
    - Music for flute and string orchestra, final ms., [(1967) final original manuscript (ink on transparency) score: 67 pieces] (Box-folder 22/1)
    - Music for flute and string orchestra, original score: movement I, [original manuscripts (and row square)] (Box-folder 22/2)
    - Music for flute and string orchestra, original score: movements II and III, [see 22/2] (Box-folder 22/3)
    - Music for flute and string orchestra, original score: movement III (cont.), [see22/2] (Box-folder 22/4)
    - Music for flute and string orchestra, original score: misc. material, [see 22/2] (Box-folder 22/5)
    - Music for flute and string orchestra, photocopied parts (6), [photo copies bound set. The flute part is printed incorrectly. 1-2 should be facing (not the usual 2-3)] (Box-folder 22/6)
    - Music for stanzas, final ms. and misc. material, [(1981) for flute, clarinet, horn, bassoon and tape (pre-taped oboe & English horn) final original manuscript (score and parts) (transparency) score: 20 pages plus title page and 3 pages of texts] (Box-folder 22/7)
    - Music for stanzas, original ms. and misc. material, [(1981) for flute, clarinet, bassoon, horn and tape. Original manuscript (such as it is) (loose pages) (rows) also sketches and source material (1 notebook and loose pages)] (Box-folder 22/8)
    - Music for stanzas, sketches and source material, [see 22/9] (Box-folder 22/9)
    - Music for stanzas, parts (3) (Box-folder 22/10)
    - Piano concerto no. 1, final ms., [(1963) final original manuscript (transparency) (ink) 89 pages] (Box-folder 23/1)
    - Piano concerto no. 1, original ms.: act I and misc. material, [(1963) original manuscript (and row chart) and other material] (Box-folder 23/2)
    - Piano concerto no. 1, original ms.: act II, [see 23/2] (Box-folder 23/3)
    - Piano concerto no. 1, original ms.: act III, [see 23/2] (Box-folder 23/4)
    - Piano concerto no. 2, final ms., [(1982) final original manuscript (transparency) 125 pages plus title page and instrumentation page] (Box-folder 23/5)
    - Piano concerto no. 2, original ms.: notebook 1 and additional material, [original manuscript (5 notebooks and 4 different rows used) {in first notebook-loose pages}] (Box-folder 24/1)
    - Piano concerto no. 2, original ms.: notebook 2, [see 24/1] (Box-folder 24/2)
    - Piano concerto no. 2, original ms.: notebook 3, [see 24/1] (Box-folder 24/3)
    - Piano concerto no. 2, original ms.: notebook 4, [see 24/1] (Box-folder 24/4)
    - Piano concerto no. 2, original ms.: notebook 5, [see 24/1] (Box-folder 24/5)
    - Quartet for flute, violin, viola, and cello; final ms., [(1960) score and parts, final original manuscript (transparencies) score: 42 pages plus “printed” title page (ink)] (Box-folder 24/6)
    - Quartet for flute, violin, viola, and cello; original ms., [(1960) original manuscript (and rows)] (Box-folder 24/7)
    - Quartet for flute, violin, viola, and cello; parts (4), [Parts: copied by Donald Stewart. Flute: 9 pages (2-3 facing). Violin: 9 pages (2-3 facing) when assembled. Viola: 9 pages (1-2 facing). Cello: 9 pages (2-3 facing).] (Box-folder 24/8)
    - Quartet for violin, flute, horn, and piano; original ms., [(1959) original manuscript and rows--basic and inv.] (Box-folder 25/1)
    - Quartet for violin, flute, horn, and piano; annotated photocopy of original ms., [(1959) photocopy of original manuscript used by publisher Margun Music, Inc. in creating publication. Original transparency destroyed in producing publications] (Box-folder 25/2)
    - Quartet for flute, violin, flute, horn, and piano; published score and parts (2 copies), [the actual publication- score and parts] (Box-folder 25/3)
    - Quintet for clarinet and strings, photocopy of final ms., [(1965) original transparency used to create publications (in which the score is in my manuscript and the parts in Donald Stewart’s) a spiral bound photocopy] (Box-folder 25/4)
    - Quintet for clarinet and strings, original ms.: notebook 1, [(1965) original manuscript (and row charts for 2 different rows)] (Box-folder 25/5)
    - Quintet for clarinet and strings, original ms.: notebook 2, [see 25/5] (Box-folder 25/6)
    - Quintet for clarinet and strings, original ms.: misc. material, [see 25/5] (Box-folder 25/7)
    - Quintet for clarinet and strings, published score and annotated parts, [Published edition, score and parts (some in my manuscript)] (Box-folder 25/8)
    - Quintet for clarinet and strings, published score and parts (Box-folder 25/9)
    - Saeculum aurem, final ms., [(1967) for flute, piano and tape. Final original manuscript (ink on transprency except for some parts of score which are photocopies) Score: 36 pages plus printed title page.] (Box-folder 26/1)